in a chemical reaction the reactants are
consumed in specific ratios based on the
Stoichiometry of the balanced chemical
equation in this equation for every one
mole of ethene three moles of oxygen gas
react we could say that the reactants
react in a one to three ratio when
there's a limiting reactant it means the
correct ratio isn't met and there will
be some leftover reactant and excess
reactant the limiting reactant is the
reactant that runs out first and
determines the maximum amount of
products that can be produced in this
problem we have two reactants 2.7 moles
of ethene reacts with 6.3 moles of o2 to
determine the limiting reactant we need
to compare these amounts to the mole
ratio of the reactants in the ballast
equation so we can calculate the number
of moles of o2 needed if all 2.7 moles
of ethylene reacts we just multiply 2.7
moles by the ratio of o2 to ethene which
is three over one so if all 2.7 moles of
ethene reacts 8.1 moles of o2 is
required however we only have 6.3 moles
of o2 not 8.1 this means that O2 is a
limiting reactant and ethine is in
excess